About 10 years ago, I went through a little bit of a hard time.
قبل 10 أعوام مضت، مررت بأوقات صعبة.
So I decided to go see a therapist.
لذلك قررت الذهاب إلى معالج نفسي.
I had been seeing her for a few months, when she looked at me one day and said,
كنت قد استمررت بمقابلتها لبضعة شهور، عنما نظرت إلي ذات يوم و قالت
"Who actually raised you until you were three?"
"من الذي رعاك بالضبط حتى صرت في عمر الثالثة؟"
Seemed like a weird question. I said, "My parents."
بدا ذلك كسؤال محير، قلت، "والداي"
And she said, "I don't think that's actually the case;
ثم قالت، "لا أعتقد أن ذلك هو السبب بالتحديد
because if it were,
لأنه إن كان الأمر كذلك،
we'd be dealing with things that are far more complicated than just this."
لكنا نتعامل الآن مع أمور أكثر تعقيدا من مجرد هذا الأمر"
It sounded like the setup to a joke, but I knew she was serious.
بدا الأمر كمزحة و لكني كنت أعلم أنها كانت جادة
Because when I first started seeing her,
لأني عندما قابلتها لأول مرة،
I was trying to be the funniest person in the room.
كنت أحاول أن أبدو الشخص الأكثر مرحا في الغرفة
And I would try and crack these jokes, but she caught on to me really quickly,
و قد أحاول ذكر بعض الدعابات، و لكنها كانت سريعا ما تلاحظ ذلك
and whenever I tried to make a joke, she would look at me and say,
و كلما حاولت رواية مزحة، كانت تنظر إليّ و تقول
"That is actually really sad."
"في الواقع ذلك أمر محزن جدا"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's terrible.
إنه شيئ فظيع.
So I knew I had to be serious, and I asked my parents
لذلك عرفت أنه كان يتوجب علي أن أكون جدية، ثم بعدها سألت والدي
who had actually raised me until I was three?
من الذي رعاني حتى صرت في عمر الثالثة؟
And to my surprise, they said
وكانت دهشتي عندما قالوا لي
my primary caregiver had been a distant relative of the family.
أن مربيتي الأولى كانت واحدة من أقرباء العائلة.
I had called her my auntie.
كنت أدعوها عمتي.
I remember my auntie so clearly,
أتذكر عمتي جيدا جدا.
it felt like she had been part of my life when I was much older.
بدا الأمر كما لو أنها كانت جزءا مني عندما أصبحت أكبر قليلا
I remember the thick, straight hair,
أتذكر شعرها الأملس و الناعم،
and how it would come around me like a curtain
و كيف كان يحيط بي مثل ستارة
when she bent to pick me up;
عندما كانت تنحني لتلتقطني
her soft, southern Thai accent;
بلكنتها التايلندية الجنوبية البسيطة
the way I would cling to her,
الطريقة التي كنت أتشبث بها،
even if she just wanted to go to the bathroom
حتى إن أرادت فقط الذهاب إلى الحمام
or get something to eat.
أو إحضار شيء لتأكله.
I loved her, but [with] the ferocity that a child has sometimes
لقد أحببتها، بكل ضراوة الطفولة
before she understands that love also requires letting go.
قبل أن تدرك أن الحب يتطلب الابتعاد أيضا.
But my clearest and sharpest memory of my auntie,
و لكن أشد ذكرياتي وضوحا ودقة بشأن عمتي
is also one of my first memories of life at all.
كانت من أوائل ذكرياتي عن الحياة على الإطلاق.
I remember her being beaten and slapped by another member of my family.
أتذكر تعرضها للضرب و الصفع من قبل أحد أفراد عائلتي.
I remember screaming hysterically and wanting it to stop,
أتذكر صياحي الهيستيري ورغبتي في وقف ذلك
as I did every single time it happened,
كما كنت أفعل في كل مرة يحدث فيها ذلك،
for things as minor as wanting to go out with her friends,
لأتفه الأسباب مثل الرغبة في الخروج مع أصدقائها
or being a little late.
أو التأخر بعض الشيء.
I became so hysterical over her treatment,
أصبحت هيستيرية جدا من طريقة معاملتها
that eventually, she was just beaten behind closed doors.
إلى أن أصبحت في آخر الأمر تُضرب خلف الأبواب الموصدة.
Things got so bad for her that eventually she ran away.
ساءت الأمور جدا بالنسبة لها لدرجة أنها هربت.
As an adult, I learned later
تعلمت لاحقا بعد أن كبرت في العمر
that she had been just 19 when she was brought over from Thailand
أنها كانت بعمر 19 سنة عندما تم جلبها من تايلند
to the States to care for me, on a tourist visa.
إلى الولايات المتحدة بتأشيرة سياحية لتعتني بي.
She wound up working in Illinois for a time,
انتهى بها الأمر أن عملت في ولاية إلينوي لبعض الوقت،
before eventually returning to Thailand,
قبل العودة إلى تايلند في آخر الأمر،
which is where I ran into her again, at a political rally in Bangkok.
حيث قابلتها مجددا، في مسيرة سياسية في بانكوك العاصمة
I clung to her again, as I had when I was a child,
تعلقت بها مجددا مثل ما كنت أفعل عندما كنت طفلة
and I let go, and then I promised that I would call.
ثم تركتها مع وعد بالاتصال.
I never did, though.
و لكن لم أفعل
Because I was afraid if I said everything that she meant to me --
لأني خشيت إن بحت بما كانت تمثل بالنسبة لي
that I owed perhaps the best parts of who I became to her care,
و أنني ربما مدينة لها اليوم بأفضل جزء مني
and that the words "I'm sorry" were like a thimble
و أن كلمات مثل "أنا آسفة" كانت مثل كشتبان الخياط
to bail out all the guilt and shame and rage I felt
لإنقاذي من إحساس الذنب والخزي و الحنق الذي اعتراني
over everything she had endured to care for me for as long as she had --
مقابل كل ما تحملته نظير رعايتها لي قدر ما استطاعت
I thought if I said those words to her, I would never stop crying again.
اعتقدت أنه بقولي لها هذه الكلمات، قد لا أتوقف عن البكاء مجددا.
Because she had saved me.
لأنها أنقذتني.
And I had not saved her.
و لكني لم أفعل لها المثل.
I'm a journalist, and I've been writing and researching human trafficking
أنا صحفية و قد ظللت أكتب و أجري أبحاثا حول الاتجار بالبشر
for the past eight years or so,
ما يقارب خلال السنوات الثمانية الماضية
and even so, I never put together this personal story
وحتى مع ذلك، لم أفهم العلاقة بين هذه القصة الشخصية
with my professional life until pretty recently.
و بين حياتي المهنية حتى وقت قريب جدا.
I think this profound disconnect actually symbolizes
أعتقد أن هذا الانقطاع العميق يرمز في الواقع إلى
most of our understanding about human trafficking.
إدراكنا لماهية مفهوم الاتجار بالبشر غالبا.
Because human trafficking is far more prevalent, complex and close to home
لأن الاتجار بالبشر أمر شائع و أكثر تعقيدا و أقرب إلينا
than most of us realize.
أكثر ممّا يظن بعضنا.
I spent time in jails and brothels,
لقد قضيت وقتا في السجون و بيوت الدعارة،
interviewed hundreds of survivors and law enforcement, NGO workers.
قابلت المئات من الناجين و منفذي القوانين وعمال منظمات المجتمع المدني.
And when I think about what we've done about human trafficking,
و عندما أفكر بقدر ما أنجزنا لإيقاف الاتجار بالبشر.
I am hugely disappointed.
أشعر بخيبة أمل عظيمة.
Partly because we don't even talk about the problem right at all.
جزء من هذه الخيبة أننا لا نتكلم حتى عن الأمر بالقدر الكافي.
When I say "human trafficking,"
عندما أقول "الاتجار بالبشر"
most of you probably don't think about someone like my auntie.
فمن المحتمل أن أغلبكم لن يفكر في شخص مثل عمتي
You probably think about a young girl or woman,
قد يتبادر إلى أذهانكم صورة فتاة شابة أو إمرأة
who's been brutally forced into prostitution by a violent pimp.
تم اجبارها بوحشية على ممارسة البغاء بواسطة قواد عنيف
That is real suffering, and that is a real story.
ذلك هو العناء الحقيقي و تلك هي القصة.
That story makes me angry
تصيبني تلك القصة بالغضب
for far more than just the reality of that situation, though.
أكثر بكثير من مجرد هذا الواقع، برغم ذلك.
As a journalist, I really care about how we relate to each other through language,
كصحفية، أهتم جدا بالكيفية التي نحكي بها قصصنا عن طريق اللغة
and the way we tell that story, with all the gory, violent detail,
و الطريقة التي نحكي بها تلك القصة بكل ما تحمله من دماء و تفاصيل عنيفة
the salacious aspects -- I call that "look at her scars" journalism.
و جوانب داعرة...أسميها بصحافة "انظر إلى ندوبها"
We use that story to convince ourselves
نستخدم تلك القصة لنقنع أنفسنا
that human trafficking is a bad man doing a bad thing to an innocent girl.
أن الاتجار بالبشر متمثل في رجل سيئ يسيئ معاملة فتاة بريئة.
That story lets us off the hook.
تلك القصة تنجينا من المأزق.
It takes away all the societal context that we might be indicted for,
يخلصنا ذلك من كامل السياق الاجتماعي الذي قد نتهم به
for the structural inequality, or the poverty,
بسبب عدم المساواة الهيكلية أو الفقر.
or the barriers to migration.
أو موانع الهجرة.
We let ourselves think
نجعل أنفسنا نفكر
that human trafficking is only about forced prostitution,
أن الاتجار بالبشر يتمحور فقط حول البغاء القسري،
when in reality,
غير أن الحقيقة،
human trafficking is embedded in our everyday lives.
أن الاتجار بالبشر متضمن في كل أشكال حياتنا اليومية.
Let me show you what I mean.
دعوني أريكم ما أعني.
Forced prostitution accounts for 22 percent of human trafficking.
يمثل البغاء القسري نسبة 22 في المئة من الاتجار بالبشر
Ten percent is in state- imposed forced labor.
عشرة في المئة في الولايات التي تفرض العمل القسري.
but a whopping 68 percent is for the purpose of creating the goods
و لكن النسبة الأعظم تصل إلى 68 في المئة بغرض خلق البضائع
and delivering the services that most of us rely on every day,
و إيصال الخدمات و التي يعتمد عليها أغلبنا يوميا،
in sectors like agricultural work, domestic work and construction.
في قطاعات مثل العمل الزراعي و العمل المنزلي والبناء.
That is food and care and shelter.
أي الغذاء والرعاية والملجأ.
And somehow, these most essential workers
و بطريقة ما، معظم هؤلاء العمال الأساسيين
are also among the world's most underpaid and exploited today.
هم أيضا ضمن أقل عمال العالم أجورا و الأكثر استغلالا اليوم.
Human trafficking is the use of force, fraud or coercion
الاتجار بالبشر هو استخدام القوة أوالاحتيال أو الإكراه
to compel another person's labor.
لتخضع شخصا آخر للعمل.
And it's found in cotton fields, and coltan mines,
و قد وجد في حقول القطن و مناجم الكولتان
and even car washes in Norway and England.
و حتى مغاسل السيارات في النرويج و إنجلترا.
It's found in U.S. military bases in Iraq and Afghanistan.
و أيضا في القواعد العسكرية الأمريكية في العراق و أفغانستان.
It's found in Thailand's fishing industry.
و حتى في مجال صناعة الصيد في تايلاند.
That country has become the largest exporter of shrimp in the world.
تلك الدولة أًصبحت أكبر مصدر للجمبري في العالم
But what are the circumstances
و لكن ما هي الظروف
behind all that cheap and plentiful shrimp?
التي ساهمت في الحصول على الجمبري الرخيص وبكمية وافرة؟
Thai military were caught selling Burmese and Cambodian migrants
تم ضبط عساكرالجيش التايلندي و هم يبيعون المهاجرين البورميين و الكمبوديين
onto fishing boats.
لقوارب السمك.
Those fishing boats were taken out, the men put to work,
بعد أن تبحر هذه القوارب يتم إخضاع الرجال للعمل
and they were thrown overboard if they made the mistake of falling sick,
و يتم إلقاؤهم من على متن القوارب في حال إصابتهم بالمرض،
or trying to resist their treatment.
أو إظهار الرفض للأوامر.
Those fish were then used to feed shrimp,
يستفاد من تلك الأسماك في إطعام الجمبري،
The shrimp were then sold to four major global retailers:
بعدها يتم بيع الجمبري لأكبر أربع تجار تجزئة عالميين:
Costco, Tesco, Walmart and Carrefour.
كوستكو وتيسكو وولمارت، وكارفور.
Human trafficking is found on a smaller scale than just that,
يوجد الاتجار بالبشر في مستوى أقل من ذلك
and in places you would never even imagine.
و في أماكن ما كان لكم أن تتخيلوها.
Traffickers have forced young people to drive ice cream trucks,
لقد أرغم تجار البشر صغارالسن على قيادة عربات بيع المثلجات
or to sing in touring boys' choirs.
أو أن يغنوا في جوقات متجولة.
Trafficking has even been found in a hair braiding salon in New Jersey.
تم ضبط عمليات متاجرة في صالون تجديل للشعر في نيو جيرسي.
The scheme in that case was incredible.
كان المخطط في تلك الواقعة لا يصدق.
The traffickers found young families who were from Ghana and Togo,
عثر المهربون على عائلات شابة تنحدر من غانا و توغو
and they told these families that "your daughters are going to get
و أخبروا تلك العائلات "إن بناتكم سيحصلن
a fine education in the United States."
على تعليم جيد في الولايات المتحدة."
They then located winners of the green card lottery,
ثم حصلوا على عناوين الفائزين في برنامج الهجرة إلى أميركا
and they told them, "We'll help you out.
و أخبروهم ، "سنساعدكم.
We'll get you a plane ticket. We'll pay your fees.
سنحضر لكم تذاكر الطيران. سندفع لكم رسومكم.
All you have to do is take this young girl with you,
كل ما يتوجب عليكم فعله هو اصطحاب هذه الفتاة معكم
say that she's your sister or your spouse.
قولوا أنها شقيقتكم أو زوجتكم.
Once everyone arrived in New Jersey, the young girls were taken away,
حين وصول الجميع إلى نيوجيرسي، تم أخذ الفتيات بعيدا
and put to work for 14-hour days,
و تم إخضاعهم إلى 14 ساعة عمل يوميا،
seven days a week, for five years.
سبعة أيام في الأسبوع و لخمس سنوات.
They made their traffickers nearly four million dollars.
جنى المهربون قرابة 4 ملايين من الدولارات.
This is a huge problem.
إنها مشكلة عظيمة.
So what have we done about it?
وبالتالي ماذا فعلنا حيالها؟
We've mostly turned to the criminal justice system.
لقد التجأنا عموما لنظام العدالة الجنائية.
But keep in mind, most victims of human trafficking are poor and marginalized.
لكن تذكروا أن أغلب ضحايا الاتجار بالبشرهم أشخاص فقراء ومهمشون
They're migrants, people of color.
هم عبارة عن مهاجرين و من عرقيات مختلفة.
Sometimes they're in the sex trade.
أحيانا هم ضحايا لتجارة الجنس.
And for populations like these,
و في مثل حالة هؤلاء،
the criminal justice system is too often part of the problem,
فإن نظام العدالة الجنائية هو غالبا جزء من المشكلة،
rather than the solution.
بدلا عن الحل.
In study after study, in countries ranging from Bangladesh to the United States,
بعد دراسات مستفيضة في دول من بنغلاديش إلى الولايات المتحدة،
between 20 and 60 percent of the people in the sex trade who were surveyed
ما بين 20 إلى 60 في المئة من الناجين من تجارة الجنس
said that they had been raped or assaulted by the police in the past year alone.
ذكروا أنه قد تم إغتصابهم أو الاعتداء عليهم من قبل الشرطة خلال السنة الماضية فقط.
People in prostitution, including people who have been trafficked into it,
الأشخاص المتورطون بالدعارة، و كذلك من يتم تهريبهم لنفس الغرض،
regularly receive multiple convictions for prostitution.
تصدر بحقهم بانتظام أحكام متعددة بممارسة الدعارة.
Having that criminal record makes it so much more difficult
لذا، مثل هذا السجل الإجرامي يجعل من الصعب للغاية
to leave poverty, leave abuse, or leave prostitution,
مغادرة دائرة الفقر، ورفض الإنتهاك أو ترك ممارسة الدعارة،
if that person so desires.
و إن كان ذلك الشخص راغباً.
Workers outside of the sex sector --
العاملون خارج قطاع الجنس
if they try and resist their treatment, they risk deportation.
إذا حاولوا مقاومة ما يتعرضون له، فإنهم يواجهون خطر الترحيل.
In case after case I've studied, employers have no problem
في كل الحالات التي درستها، فإن أرباب العمل لا يترددون
calling on law enforcement to try and threaten or deport
بالاتصال بالجهات التنفيذية لمحاولة تهديد أو ترحيل
their striking trafficked workers.
عمالهم المهربين المضربين عن العمل
If those workers run away,
إذا حاول هؤلاء العمال الهرب،
they risk becoming part of the great mass of undocumented workers
فهم يخاطرون بأن ينضموا لمجموعة كبيرة من العمال غير المسجلين
who are also subject to the whims of law enforcement if they're caught.
و الذين هم أيضا معرضون لنزوات الجهات التنفيذية في حال تم القبض عليهم.
Law enforcement is supposed to identify victims and prosecute traffickers.
يتوجب على الجهات التنفيذية تحديد هوية الضحايا و محاكمة المهربين.
But out of an estimated 21 million victims of human trafficking in the world,
و لكن من بين 21 مليون ضحية لعمليات الاتجار بالبشر في العالم،
they have helped and identified fewer than 50,000 people.
فقد ساعدت هذه الجهات و تعرفت على أقل من 50000 شخص.
That's like comparing
هذا مثل مقارنة
the population of the world to the population of Los Angeles,
عدد سكان العالم بعدد سكان لوس أنجلوس،
proportionally speaking.
بالمعنى النسبي.
As for convictions, out of an estimated 5,700 convictions in 2013,
فيما يتعلق بالأحكام، ما يقدر ب 5700 حكم تقرّر في عام 2013،
fewer than 500 were for labor trafficking.
أقل من 500 كان لصالح الاتجار بالبشر.
Keep in mind that labor trafficking
تذكروا أن الاتجار بغرض العمل
accounts for 68 percent of all trafficking,
تعتبر نسبته 68 في المئة من مجمل حركة التهريب،
but fewer than 10 percent of the convictions.
مقابل أقل من 10 في المئة من الأحكام.
I've heard one expert say that trafficking happens where need meets greed.
لقد سمعت أحد الخبراء يقول أن الاتجار يحدث عندما تجتمع الحاجة مع الطمع.
I'd like to add one more element to that.
أود إضافة عنصر آخر لذلك،
Trafficking happens in sectors where workers are excluded from protections,
يحدث الاتجار في القطاعات التي يستثنى فيها العمال من الحماية،
and denied the right to organize.
و ينكر فيها الحق في النظام.
Trafficking doesn't happen in a vacuum.
الاتجار لا يحدث من فراغ.
It happens in systematically degraded work environments.
إنه يحدث في بيئات عمل متدهورة بشكل منهجي
You might be thinking,
ربما تفكرون.
oh, she's talking about failed states, or war-torn states, or --
أوه، أنها تتحدث عن دول فاشلة، أو دول مزقتها الحروب، أو...
I'm actually talking about the United States.
أنا في الواقع أتحدث عن الولايات المتحدة.
Let me tell you what that looks like.
دعوني أخبركم كيف يبدو عليه الأمر.
I spent many months researching a trafficking case called Global Horizons,
لقد قضيت عدة شهور أبحث في قضية تهريب تسمى آفاق عالمية،
involving hundreds of Thai farm workers.
تشمل المئات من عمال المزارع التايلنديين.
They were sent all over the States, to work in Hawaii pineapple plantations,
تم إرسالهم إلى مختلف الولايات ليعملوا في مزارع الأناناس المنسوب إلى هاواي،
and Washington apple orchards, and anywhere the work was needed.
و بساتين التفاح الأمريكي، و إلى كل مكان كان فيه حاجة للعمل.
They were promised three years of solid agricultural work.
وعدوا بثلاث سنين من العمل الزراعي الجاد.
So they made a calculated risk.
فقاموا بعملية حساب مخاطرة.
They sold their land, they sold their wives' jewelry,
باعوا أراضيهم و مجوهرات زوجاتهم،
to make thousands in recruitment fees for this company, Global Horizons.
ليدفعوا الآلاف هي رسوم توظيفهم في شركة الآفاق العالمية.
But once they were brought over,
و حين تم جلبهم،
their passports were confiscated.
تم مصادرة جوازات سفرهم.
Some of the men were beaten and held at gunpoint.
تعرض بعض الرجال للضرب و الحبس تحت تهديد السلاح.
They worked so hard they fainted in the fields.
عملوا بشكل قاسٍ لدرجة أنه أغمي عليهم في الحقول.
This case hit me so hard.
هذه القضية أثرت فيّ كثيرا.
After I came back home,
بعد أن عدت إلى الديار،
I was wandering through the grocery store, and I froze in the produce department.
كنت أتجول في البقالة، ثم تجمدت أمام وحدة الإنتاج.
I was remembering the over-the-top meals the Global Horizons survivors
كنت أتذكر وجبات الطعام التي كان يعدها لي الناجون
would make for me every time I showed up to interview them.
من شركة آفاق عالمية في كل مرة ألتقيهم فيها.
They finished one meal with this plate of perfect, long-stemmed strawberries,
أعدوا إحدى الوجبات من طبق الفراولة الرائع و طويل الساق هذا
and as they handed them to me, they said,
و إذا هم يمدونه لي قالوا،
"Aren't these the kind of strawberries you eat with somebody special
"أليست هذه هي نوع الفراولة التي تأكلينها برفقة شخص عزيز عليك
in the States?
في الولايات المتحدة؟
And don't they taste so much better
ألا تبدو أحلى مذاقا
when you know the people whose hands picked them for you?"
عندما تلتقين الأشخاص الذين يقطفونها لكم بأيديهم؟"
As I stood in that grocery store weeks later, I realized I had no idea
و يينما أنا أقف في نفس المتجر بعدها بعدة أسابيع، لاحظت أني في حيرة
of who to thank for this plenty,
من يجب أن أشكر مقابل هذه الوفرة.
and no idea of how they were being treated.
و لا فكرة لدي عن كيف كانت تتم معاملتهم.
So, like the journalist I am, I started digging into the agricultural sector.
لذا، بحس الصحفي لدي بدأت النتقيب في القطاع الزراعي
And I found there are too many fields, and too few labor inspectors.
فوجدت الكثير من الحقول و القليل جدا من مفتشي العمالة
I found multiple layers of plausible deniability
وجدت طبقات متعددة من سياسة الإنكار
between grower and distributor and processor, and God knows who else.
بين المزارع و الموزع و المعالج، و الله يعلم مَنْ أيضا.
The Global Horizons survivors had been brought to the States
الناجون من شركة آفاق عالمية تم جلبهم إلى الولايات المتحدة
on a temporary guest worker program.
تبعا لبرنامج العامل الضيف المؤقت.
That guest worker program ties a person's legal status
يقيد هذا البرنامج حالة الشخص القانونية
to his or her employer,
إلى رب العمل،
and denies that worker the right to organize.
و ينكر حقه في توفيق أوضاعه.
Mind you, none of what I am describing about this agricultural sector
تذكروا، لا شيء من ما أصِفُه حول هذا القطاع الزراعي
or the guest worker program is actually human trafficking.
أو عن برنامج العامل الضيف ما يعتبر تجارة بالبشر.
It is merely what we find legally tolerable.
هو مجرد ما نجده مقبولاً قانونياً.
And I would argue this is fertile ground for exploitation.
و أنا أجزم أن هذه تربة خصبة للاستغلال.
And all of this had been hidden to me, before I had tried to understand it.
و كل هذا كان مخفيا عني، قبل محاولتي لفهمه.
I wasn't the only person grappling with these issues.
لم أكن الشخص الوحيد الذي يتصارع مع هذه القضايا.
Pierre Omidyar, founder of eBay,
بيير أوميديار و هو مؤسس موقع إيباي،
is one of the biggest anti-trafficking philanthropists in the world.
هو فاعل خير و من أشد المعارضين لتجارة البشر في العالم.
And even he wound up accidentally investing nearly 10 million dollars
حتى أنه انتهى به الأمر مصادفة باستثمار قرابة 10 ملايين من الدولارات
in the pineapple plantation cited as having the worst working conditions
في مزارع الأناناس التي استشهدت بها لاحتوائها على أسوء ظروف عمل
in that Global Horizons case.
كما في حالة شركة الآفاق العالمية.
When he found out, he and his wife were shocked and horrified,
عندما اكتشف ذلك، أصيب هو وزوجته بالصدمة و الرعب
and they wound up writing an op-ed for a newspaper,
و تطلب الأمر منهم كتابة افتتاحية لصحيفة
saying that it was up to all of us to learn everything we can
قائلين أن الأمر كان متروكا لنا جميعا لنتعلم كل ما يمكن
about the labor and supply chains of the products that we support.
عن العمالة و سلاسل الإمداد للمنتجات التي ندعمها.
I totally agree.
من جهتي فأنا أوافق بشدة.
What would happen if each one of us decided
ماذا يمكن أن يحدث إن قرر كل فرد منا
that we are no longer going to support companies
أنه لن يواصل دعم الشركات
if they don't eliminate exploitation from their labor and supply chains?
في حال لم يقضوا على الاستغلال الموجه ضد العمالة و سلاسل التزويد؟
If we demanded laws calling for the same?
إذا ما طالبنا بقوانين تدعو لنفس الهدف؟
If all the CEOs out there decided
إذا ما قرر كل رؤساء الشركات التنفيذيين
that they were going to go through their businesses and say, "no more"?
أنهم سيراجعون أعمالهم التجارية و يقولون، "كفى"؟
If we ended recruitment fees for migrant workers?
إذا ما ألغينا رسوم الاستقدام المفروضة على العمال المهاجرين؟
If we decided that guest workers should have the right to organize
إذا ما قررنا أن العمال المستضافين لهم الحق في توفيق أوضاعهم
without fear of retaliation?
من غير خوف من الانتقام؟
These would be decisions heard around the world.
يمكن أن تكون هذه قرارت يتردد صداها حول العالم.
This isn't a matter of buying a fair-trade peach
ليس الأمر مثل أن تشتري خوخا بسعر مناسب
and calling it a day, buying a guilt-free zone with your money.
و ينتهي الأمر، أو أن تشتري بأموالك منطقة متاحة للبيع.
That's not how it works.
ليس هكذا تجري الأمور.
This is the decision to change a system that is broken,
المطلوب هو قرار لتغيير نظام معتل
and that we have unwittingly but willingly
و أننا بشكل عفوي و لكن برغبتنا
allowed ourselves to profit from and benefit from for too long.
سمحنا لأنفسنا أن نربح و نستفيد منه لزمن طويل.
We often dwell on human trafficking survivors' victimization.
نحن أحيانا نفيض في الحيث عن الناجين من الاتجار بالبشر
But that is not my experience of them.
و لكن تلك ليست هي كل تجربتي معهم.
Over all the years that I've been talking to them,
بعد كل السنين التي قضيتها أتحدث إليهم،
they have taught me that we are more than our worst days.
علموني أنهم ليسوا أكبر مشاكلنا.
Each one of us is more than what we have lived through.
كل واحد منا هو أكبر من ما عانى من مشاكل.
Especially trafficking survivors.
و بخاصة الناجون من الاتجار.
These people were the most resourceful and resilient and responsible
كان هؤلاء الناس هم الأكثر مقدرة و مرونة و أصحاب مسؤولية
in their communities.
في مجتمعاتهم.
They were the people that you would take a gamble on.
كانوا من الذين يمكن أن تراهن عليهم.
You'd say, I'm gong to sell my rings, because I have the chance
قد تقول، سأبيع خواتمي لأنني سأحظى بفرصة
to send you off to a better future.
للسفر من أجل حياة أفضل.
They were the emissaries of hope.
لقد كانوا مبعوثين من الأمل
These survivors don't need saving.
هؤلاء الناجين ليسوا بحاجة للإنقاذ.
They need solidarity, because they're behind
هم بحاجة إلى التضامن لأنهم السبب وراء
some of the most exciting social justice movements out there today.
وجود مظاهرات تطالب بالعدالة الاجتماعية هذه الأيام
The nannies and housekeepers who marched with their families
مثل المربيات و مدبرات المنازل اللاتي سرن في مسيرات مع عائلاتهن
and their employers' families --
و عائلات مخدوميهن
their activism got us an international treaty
ضمن لنا نشاطهم حصولنا على معاهدة دولية
on domestic workers' rights.
تتعلق بحقوق العمال المنزليين.
The Nepali women who were trafficked into the sex trade --
النساء النيباليات اللاتي تم تهريبهن لتعمل في تجارة الجنس
they came together, and they decided
اتحدن مع بعضهن و قررن
that they were going to make the world's first anti-trafficking organization
أنهن سيؤسسن أول منظمة مناهضة للاتجار بالبشر في العالم
actually headed and run by trafficking survivors themselves.
يترأسها و يديرها الناجون من الاتجار بأنفسهم
These Indian shipyard workers were trafficked
عمال السفن الهنود هؤلاء تم تهريبهم
to do post-Hurricane Katrina reconstruction.
ليقوموا بأعمال البناء ما بعد إعصاركاترينا.
They were threatened with deportation, but they broke out of their work compound
تم تهديدهم بالترحيل، و لكن اندفعوا خارج مجمع العمل
and they marched from New Orleans to Washington, D.C.,
و ساروا من نيوأورليانز إلى واشنطن العاصمة.
to protest labor exploitation.
لكي يحتجوا ضد استغلال العمالة.
They cofounded an organization called the National Guest Worker Alliance,
أنشؤوا منظمة مع آخرين تدعى تحالف العامل الضيف القومي
and through this organization, they have wound up helping other workers
و من خلال هذه المنظمة ساعدوا بقية العمال
bring to light exploitation and abuses in supply chains
بتسليط الضوء على الاستغلال والإنتهاكات في سلاسل الإمداد
in Walmart and Hershey's factories.
في مصانع وولمرت و هيرشي.
And although the Department of Justice declined to take their case,
و على الرغم من أن قسم العدالة رفض أن ينظر في قضيتهم
a team of civil rights lawyers won the first of a dozen civil suits
إلا أن فريقا من محامي الحقوق المدنية ربحوا أول دعوى مدنية من بين العشرات
this February, and got their clients 14 million dollars.
في فبراير الحالي، و جلبوا لموكليهم 14 مليون دولار.
These survivors are fighting for people they don't even know yet,
هؤلاء الناجين يقاتلون من أجل أناس لا يعرفونهم حتى الآن،
other workers, and for the possibility of a just world for all of us.
من أجل عمال آخرين، فقط لأجل خلق عالم يسعنا جميعا.
This is our chance to do the same.
هذه فرصتنا لفعل المثل.
This is our chance to make the decision
هذه فرصتنا لنتخذ القرار
that tells us who we are, as a people and as a society;
الذي يعبر عنا، كبشر و كمجتمع
that our prosperity is no longer prosperity,
أن ازدهارنا لن يعد ازدهارا بعد الآن،
as long as it is pinned to other people's pain;
طالما أنه يدور حول آلام أناس آخرين،
that our lives are inextricably woven together;
أن حياتنا مرتبطة مع بعضها بشكل معقد
and that we have the power to make a different choice.
و أننا نمتلك القدرة للقيام بشيئ مختلف.
I was so reluctant to share my story of my auntie with you.
كنت مترددة أن أشارككم قصة عمتي.
Before I started this TED process and climbed up on this stage,
قبل أن أبدأ مشاركتي بTED و أعتلي هذه المنصة
I had told literally a handful of people about it,
أخبرت حرفيا العديد من الناس حول الأمر
because, like many a journalist,
و السبب مثل كثير من الصحافيين،
I am far more interested in learning about your stories
أنا مهتمة جدا بمعرفة قصصكم
than sharing much, if anything, about my own.
أكثر من مشاركة أي شيء يخصني.
I also haven't done my journalistic due diligence on this.
كما أني لم أقم بواجبي الصحفي بهمة في شأن هذا الأمر
I haven't issued my mountains of document requests,
لم أنشر ما بحوزتي من وثائق الطلبات،
and interviewed everyone and their mother,
ولم أقابل كل شخص و أمه،
and I haven't found my auntie yet.
و لم ألتقي عمتي بعد.
I don't know her story of what happened, and of her life now.
لا أعرف تفاصيل ما حدث لها وعن حياتها الآن.
The story as I've told it to you is messy and unfinished.
وكما أخبرتكم القصة مشوشة وغير مكتملة.
But I think it mirrors the messy and unfinished situation we're all in,
و لكني أعتقد أنها تعكس حالة الفوضى والوضع غير المكتمل الذي نحن فيه،
when it comes to human trafficking.
عنما يتعلق الأمر بالاتجار بالبشر.
We are all implicated in this problem.
جميعنا متورطون في هذه المشكلة.
But that means we are all also part of its solution.
و هذا يعني أننا جزء من الحل.
Figuring out how to build a more just world is our work to do,
يتوجّب علينا معرفة كيفية بناء أكثر من عالم أفضل
and our story to tell.
و هي قصتنا التي سنورويها.
So let us tell it the way we should have done,
لذا دعونا نخبر عنها بالطريقة الواجبة لذلك،
from the very beginning.
من البداية.
Let us tell this story together.
دعونا نحكي القصة معا.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)